Guide to the Jacob Harvey Family Papers 1811-1994 MS 306
New-York Historical Society
Jacob Harvey family papers
1811-1994
New-York Historical Society
Harvey, Jacob, 1797-1848
MS 306
8.75 Linear feet in five record cartons, nine document boxes, and one oversized folder.
The collection contains just under four linear feet of 19th century material, including correspondence, journals, and miscellaneous ephemera belonging to New York merchant and Quaker Jacob Harvey (1797-1848), his wife Mary Hosack Harvey (1800-1872), and their daughters Mary Harvey (1831-1900) and Rebecca Harvey (1840-1912). The bulk of the 19th century material consists of journals and correspondence belonging to Jacob Harvey, and is concerned with politics in the United States and Great Britain, the Society of Friends, Harvey's business affairs, and his humanitarian efforts. Correspondence and other materials belonging to Mary H., Mary, and Rebecca Harvey are primarily concerned with life and society in New York City and its environs. Also included in the collection are typescripts, an index, and research notes prepared and compiled by historians Claire and Daniel Feins through the middle of the 20th century. Much of the 20th century material relates to the Harvey family, though a significant portion of the Feinses research notes are concerned with the life and work of prominent New York physician, and father to Mary H. Harvey, David Hosack.
Biographical/Historical Note
In 1939, Claire Feins, a graduate student in history at Columbia University, took an interest in prominent New York physician, botanist, and founding member of New-York Historical Society, David Hosack (1769-1835). Feins began to research his life and work while writing a history of Columbia University's Rockefeller Center property to satisfy her master's thesis. Following the completion of her degree, Feins continued to build upon her research, with the intent of using it as the subject for a doctoral thesis. In 1948 she applied for a John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Fellowship to write a biography of David Hosack, but did not receive funding for her project, and never completed her dissertation.
Over the course of her research, Feins made contact with sisters Alice, Constance, and Georgina Biddle, descendants of David Hosack, who provided her with access to their family papers. At the time, these papers were thought to contain primary source material pertaining to the life of David Hosack, but Feins found little that was of any use to her. There was, however, a substantial amount of correspondence belonging to Hosack's immediate family, specifically his daughter, Mary Hosack Harvey (1800-1872), and her husband, Jacob Harvey (1797-1848). While Feins continued her Hosack research, her husband, Daniel Feins, who was inspired by the quality and extent the Harvey manuscripts, began to push for a publication based upon the Harvey material.
Although Claire Feins did not write her book on David Hosack, one was eventually written by Christine Chapman Robbins, and published by the American Philosophical Society [APS]. Feins appears to have lent some assistance to this work, and an inscribed copy, from Robbins to Feins, is in the collection. Preceding the publication of this volume, in 1962, the Feinses lent a portion of the Jacob Harvey correspondence and other materials to APS, which were microfilmed and returned to the Feinses.
Jacob Harvey was an Irish merchant, and Quaker, who emigrated to the United States in 1816, where he began his career as an apprentice to Abraham Bell, of A. Bell & Co. in New York. In 1822, Bell took Harvey as partner in his firm, and Harvey became deeply involved in the commercial life of the city. 1827 saw his break with the Society of Friends, owing primarily to a controversy between the Orthodox in England and the New Lights in New York, as well as his romantic interest in women not of the same religious persuasion. In 1828 he married Mary Hosack who was the daughter of prominent New York physician David Hosack, and together they had two daughters, Mary Harvey (1831-1900) and Rebecca Harvey (1840-1912).
Throughout his life, Jacob Harvey was distinctly politically engaged, writing letters to such prominent figures as Andrew Jackson, James K. Polk, John Randolph of Roanoke, William H. Seward, Martin van Buren, and Daniel Webster, among others. Harvey was acutely aware of the problems of his homeland and its people, and, with the aid of A. Bell & Co., raised money and food for Irish relief during the famine, and assisted Irish immigrants in locating lost relatives and remitting hard earned money to Ireland. Harvey was also deeply concerned by the institution of slavery in the United States, and frequently advocated for the rights of enslaved persons.
Scope and Contents Note
The collection includes just under four linear feet of 19th century material, including correspondence, journals, and miscellaneous ephemera belonging to the Harvey family. The Harvey family papers are primarily concerned with life, society, and politics in the United States and Great Britain, the Society of Friends, and Jacob Harvey's business affairs and humanitarian efforts, as well as his political views and extensive travels.
Jacob Harvey engaged in brief correspondence with such prominent American politicians as Andrew Jackson, James K. Polk, and Martin van Buren, among others, but he maintained a robust correspondence with several influential figures in Great Britain. Of particular interest are his ample correspondence with George William Frederick Howard, 7th Earl of Carlisle, T. Spring Rice, Baron Monteagle of Brandon, the Marquess of Lansdowne, and the Marquess of Sligo.
A significant portion of the collection consists of 20th century materials, including typescripts, an index, and research notes which were prepared and compiled by historians Claire and Daniel Feins. Although much of this material relates to the Harvey family papers, a significant portion of the Feinses research notes are concerned with the life and work of prominent 19th century physician, David Hosack.
Arrangement Note
The collection is arranged first by format, opening with the typescripts and an index prepared by the Feinses circa 1950. This is followed by the 19th century Harvey family papers, and finally by research notes compiled by the Feinses between 1930 and 1960.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
Gift of Roberta Feins, daughter of Claire and Daniel Feins, 2000.
Related Archival Materials Note
Related materials at New-York Historical Society include:
Abraham Bell & Son. .: Call Number: Abraham Bell & Son records
Abraham Bell & Son records supplement,1833-1853.
Hosack, David, 1769-1835.: Call Number: AHMC - Hosack, David
Rodgers, Emily Hosack, (Mrs. John Kearny), 1810-1893.: Call Number: AHMC - Rodgers, Emily Hosack
Related materials at American Philosophical Society include:
Jacob Harvey papers,1808-1847
William H. (William Henry) Harvey papers, 1848-1865
Immigrants -- United States -- History -- 19th century.; Linen industry -- Northern Ireland -- History -- 19th century.; Quakers; Slavery -- Political aspects -- History -- 19th century.; Baltimore (Md.) -- Description and travel.; Canada -- Description and travel.; Great Britain -- Description and travel.; Ireland -- History -- Famine, 1845-1852.; New York (N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.) -- Description and travel.; United States -- Description and travel.; United States -- Politics and government -- 19th century.; Washington (D.C.) -- Description and travel.; West (U.S.) -- Description and travel.; Bell, Abraham, 1778-1856 -- Correspondence; Harvey family -- Correspondence; Harvey, Jacob, 1797-1848 -- Correspondence; Harvey, William H. (William Henry), 1811-1866 -- Correspondence; Hosack, David, 1769-1835; Randolph, John, 1773-1833 -- Correspondence
- Series I. Jacob Harvey Typescripts and Index, circa 1950; 2 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series comprises typescripts, prepared by the Feinses, of a selection of the Jacob Harvey correspondence and journals found in the collection, as well as index cards indexing a selection of the correspondence.
  Arrangement Note
  Typescripts of the Jacob Harvey correspondence are situated at the beginning of the series and organized chronologically. These are followed by notecards which index a portion of the correspondence, and typescripts of selected journals.
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1808-1816, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1808-1816 (carbon 1), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1808-1816 (carbon 2), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1817, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1817 (carbon 1), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1817 (carbon 2), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1818-1819, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1818-1819 (carbon 1), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1818-1819 (carbon 2), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1820, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1820 (carbon 1), cica 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1820 (carbon 2), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1821, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1821 (carbon 1), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1821 (carbon 2), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1822, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1822 (carbon 1), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1822 (carbon 2), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1823, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1823 (carbon 1), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Jacob Harvey to Family, 1823 (carbon 2), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Typescript. Correspondence, Original returned presumably to J.H. Barnes, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    Includes three typescripts whose original letters are not part of the collection. Correspondents include: Daniel Webster (1839); Maria Edgeworth (1843); Samuel Lover (1846).
  - Notecards. Index to Harvey Correspondence, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Cards --)
    Set of index cards indexing a portion of the Harvey correspondence between the years of 1816 and 1846. Cards are arranged chronologically and index letters by correspondent as well as by subject matter. Subjects include: Humanitarian - Quaker Affairs, Slavery; American Scene - Travels, Social, Literary; American Scene - Political International; Irish, English - Anglo-Irish Affairs; New York Scene - Social, Political-Personal; Business - Commercial.
  - Typescript. Proceedings of the Yearly Meeting in Philadelphia in 1820, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    This typescript appears to have been copied from the journal titled Account of the Yearly Meeting in Philadelphia (2 of 2), which is assumed to be a copy — or final draft — of Account of the Yearly Meeting in Philadelphia (1 of 2). The typescript is an excerpt only, and consists of about one third of the account in its entirety. Both journals also record the proceedings of the Yearly Meeting in New York in 1820. This typescript does not include any part of that account.
  - Typescript. Proceedings of the Yearly Meeting in Philadelphia in 1820 (carbon 1), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Typescript. Proceedings of the Yearly Meeting in Philadelphia in 1820 (carbon 2), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Typescript. Journal, Tour to the Falls of Niagara in 1820, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    This typescript appears to have been copied from the journal titled Tour to the Falls of Niagara and Canada (2 of 2), which is assumed to be a copy — or final draft — of Tour to the Falls of Niagara and Canada (1 of 2).
  - Typescript. Journal, Tour to the Falls of Niagara in 1820 (carbon 1), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Typescript. Journal, Tour to the Falls of Niagara in 1820 (carbon 2), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Typescript. Journal, Tour to the Falls of Niagara in 1820 (carbon 3), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Typescript. Journal, Voyage Round Long Island, 1821, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    This typescript appears to have been copied from the journal titled Voyage Round Long Island.
  - Typescript. Journal, Voyage Round Long Island, 1821 (carbon 1), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - Typescript. Journal, Voyage Round Long Island, 1821 (carbon 2), circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Typescript. Journal Extracts, circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
- Series II. Harvey Family Papers, 1808-1950; 3.75 Linear feet
  This series comprises the correspondence of Jacob Harvey and his wife Mary Hosack Harvey, as well as that of their daughters Mary and Rebecca Harvey. Also included are journals kept by Jacob and Rebecca Harvey, a scrapbook belonging to Mary Hosack Harvey, miscellaneous correspondence, literary efforts, and ephemera, and research notes compiled by the Feinses.
  The series is organized in six subseries:
  Subseries II.A. Jacob Harvey Correspondence
  Subseries II.B. Jacob Harvey Journals
  Subseries II.C. Mary Hosack Harvey Correspondence and Scrapbook
  Subseries II.D. Mary Harvey Correspondence
  Subseries II.E. Rebecca Harvey Correspondence and Journal
  Subseries II.F. Miscellaneous
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
  - Subseries II.A. Jacob Harvey Correspondence, 1808-1848; 1.67 Linear feet
    This subseries comprises Jacob Harvey's correspondence between the years 1808 and 1848, in addition to newspaper clippings and miscellaneous literary efforts, both collected and written by Harvey.
    Jacob Harvey's correspondence covers a wide variety of subjects. Letters to and from his family, particularly his father, discuss commercial information, business conditions, local and national news, as well as English politics and Irish problems. Until roughly 1827, many of Harvey's letters are concerned with Quaker affairs in the United States, and the conflict between the the Orthodox Quakers of England, and the New Lights in New York.
    In many of his letters Harvey examines the social, political, and literary scenes in the United States, and his correspondence is frequently engaged in a discussion of personal and public opinions on such subjects as the rights of Native Americans, the institution of slavery, universal suffrage, and democracy. Foreign affairs occupy much of Harvey's correspondence as well, and Irish immigration, especially in New York, comes under Harvey's scrutiny, as do the Maine and Oregon boundary disputes, and the Erie Canal. A number of notable correspondents appear in the subseries, including DeWitt Clinton, James Fenimore Cooper, Andrew Jackson, James K. Polk, John Randolph of Roanoke, William H. Seward, Martin van Buren, and Daniel Webster. The container list identifies all correspondents, along with notable subjects at the folder level. The subject notes are not comprehensive as they are based in large part upon the Feins's summaries found in the collection.
    Overall, the subseries is arranged by correspondent, with documents other than correspondence situated at the end of the subseries. The correspondence is further arranged as follows:
    Correspondence between Jacob Harvey and his family is situated at the beginning of the subseries, and is arranged chronologically. Following this, correspondents represented by several letters, or who are especially notable, are arranged alphabetically and foldered by the surname, whereas correspondents represented by three or fewer letters are foldered together. These are followed by letters to or from unidentified correspondents.
    Some effort was made to maintain the order imposed by the Feinses, however, for the sake of continuity, this order was sometimes disrupted. Many folders include fragments of the Feins's envelopes that at one time housed the Harvey correspondence, as the Feinses often recorded notes about the contents.
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Father), 1808-1815 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
      These letters are unique from the rest of the correspondence between Harvey and his family in that Harvey wrote them as a child, while he was away from home, at school in Ballitore.
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1816 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1817 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1818 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1819 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1820 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1821 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1822 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1823 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1824 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1825 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1826 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1827-1829 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mother & Father), 1830-1834 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    - Jacob Harvey to Family (Mary Hosack Harvey, Mary (Molly) Harvey, William Henry Harvey), 1838-1848 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    - Family to Jacob Harvey (Hannah Harvey, Rebecca Harvey, Mother & Father), 1810-1829 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes one letter to Mary Hosack Harvey from W.H. Harvey (April 29, 1829).
    - Family to Jacob Harvey (Hannah Harvey, Mother & Father), 1830-1836 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
    - Family to Jacob Harvey (James Harvey), 1840-1847 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
      Includes copies of correspondence between James Harvey and Lord Lansdowne which had accompanied a letter sent by James Harvey to Jacob Harvey, as well as one letter from Hannah Harvey to Jacob Harvey and one letter from an unidentified correspondent to Jacob Harvey.
    - Jacob Harvey to Lord Aberdeen, 1840s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
      One letter.
    - Jacob Harvey to Lord Ashburton, 1842 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Abraham Bell, 1824-1847 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
      Abraham Bell was the cousin of Jacob Harvey and the person who accompanied him to the United States in 1816. Bell took Harvey as an apprentice and, in 1822, as a partner in the firm of A. Bell & Co. Bell was also a prominant Quaker in New York. Correspondence between Harvey and Bell is predominantly concerned with their business affairs.
    - Jacob Harvey from Robert Benson, 1824-1830 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
      Robert Benson appears to have been an English Quaker who sided with the Braithwaites in their conflict with Elias Hicks in New York. The conflict was a facet of the schism between the Orthodox of English Society, and the New Lights led by Hicks. Correspondence between Harvey and Benson is ample, is concerned predominantly with Quaker affairs in the United States and in England.
    - Jacob Harvey about Braithwaite - "Calumny Refuted or Plain facts versus misrepresentations, being a reply to a pamphlet entitled 'The Misrepresentations of Anna Braithwaite in relation to the doctrines preached by Elias Hicks.'", 1820s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
      This manuscript is a copy of a work published by Jacob Harvey in defense of Anna Braithwaite during a heated public conflict which was a facet of the schism between the Orthodox Quakers in England, and the New Lights in New York.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Isaac and Anna Braithwaite, 1824-1828 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
      The letters in this folder had been arranged by Feinses in an envelope titled "Quaker Matters," and pertain to Quaker affairs in the United States and England. Much of the correspondence is concerned with a conflict which was a facet of the schism between the Orthodox in England, of which the Braithwaites were members, and the New Lights, led by Hicks in New York. The folder also includes a memorandum of a visit by George and Ann Jones to Abraham Bell's family as well as copies of a letter to George Jones, written by Jacob Harvey, which detail an incident between the Jones, who were English Quakers also opposed to Hicks, and the Bells. Also included is a letter from Thomas Wright to Jacob Harvey on the subject of this incident.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from William Brown, 1839-1847 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
      Correspondence between Brown and Harvey is primarily concerned with the Maine and Oregon boundary disputes.
    - Jacob Harvey from William C. Bryant, 1842 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
    - Jacob Harvey to Charles Buller, 1841-1846 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
      Correspondence between Buller and Harvey is primarily concerned with the Maine and Oregon boundary disputes.
    - Jacob Harvey from Benjamin F. Butler, 1839 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
      One letter concerning a Mr. Fairchild.
    - Jacob Harvey from Joseph Cecil, 1823-1824 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
      Three letters concerned with life and society in Ireland, England and the United States. Brief references are made to Randolph, international politics, and business affairs.
    - Jacob Harvey from Eliza F. Clibborn, 1826-1846 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
      Letters expressing concern about an unidentified matter. Includes one letter from an unidentified correspondent to Mr. Clibborn.
    - Jacob Harvey from DeWitt Clinton, 1824-1827 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
      Two letters concerning the exchange of published works on the topics of Ireland and the United States.
    - Jacob Harvey from David C. Colden & Maria Colden, 1823-1827 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
      Three letters concerning life and society in England and the United States.
    - Jacob Harvey from James Fenimore Cooper, 1842 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
    - Jacob Harvey from Thomas P. Cope, 1826 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
      One letter comprising an extract from the Journals of Congress, 1783.
    - Jacob Harvey from Coster Family, 1829-1830 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22)
      Several letters from Adeline Coster, Caroline Coster, and Laura Coster, all generally on the topics of life and society in New York.